玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的时间 空间和物质
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
它是创造与毁灭的大熔炉
lt's a crucible of creation and destruction.
"银河"这名字听上去的感觉…
The name "Milky Way" sounds like something...
舒心 恬静
kind of comforting and sweet.
然而银河系却是个怪物
But the Milky Way galaxy is a monster.
它只是数十亿个星系中的一个而我们处在其边缘
lt's just one galaxy among billions, and we're living on the edge.
不久前我们发现了两个小星系
Just recently, we've discovered that there are two small galaxies...
目前正与银河系发生碰撞
colliding with the Milky Way right now.
它是一条明亮的恒星与大团尘埃组成的挂毯
lt's a tapestry of brilliant suns and blinding dust.
令人惊奇的是从我们相当明亮的银河系
lt's surprising how little of the light...
抵达我们的光线相当的少
from our rather luminous Milky Way galaxy reaches us.
这是个极端的地方 在这里恒星可以慢吞吞地漂移
lt's a place of extremes, where stars can drift lazily...
或者每小时被甩出百万多英里
or be flung out at more than a million miles per hour.
现在科学家已经透过星系昏暗的中心
Now scientists have pierced the galaxy's heart of darkness...
去找到穿越银河的出路
to find ourway through the Milky Way.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第四集 银河系
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 04of19 Milky.Way
它直径有10万光年
lt's 100,000 light-years in diameter...
质量比我们的太阳大万亿倍
has a trillion times more mass than our Sun.
它诞生于130亿年前
lt began about thirteen billion years ago...
目前仍然在构建之中
and is still under construction.
这就是我们的星系 银河系
lt's our galaxy, the Milky Way.
银河系是一个极其活跃的地方
The Milky Way galaxy is an extremely active place.
它就像一个建设项目
lt's like a construction project.
一切一直都在发生变化
There's things going on all the time.
你可以看到年长的恒星死亡 摧毁
You have old stars dying and torn down...
然后这些物质被用来建造全新的恒星
and then that material gets used to build brand-new stars.
在这个作业区内
ln the midst of this work zone...
坐落有我们小小的太阳系 还有很多很多
lies our little solar system and a whole lot more.
我想最好是将银河系看作是我们的恒星大家庭
l suppose the best way to think of the Milky Way galaxy...is ourfamily of stars.
那些成群结伴恒星穿梭在宇宙间
These are the stars that we travel through the universe with...
都围绕着共同的中心运行
in a clump, all orbiting a common center.
在其展开的螺旋臂里
Within its far-reaching spiral arms...
深藏着我们诞生和如何消亡的线索
lie clues to where we started...and how it all will end.
在晴朗的夏夜 银河系里的群星
On a clear summer night, the stars of the Milky Way...
像闪闪发光的旗帜展开在夜空
unfurl like a shimmering banner across the sky.
古埃及人将这条星河看作是
Ancient Egyptians saw this river of stars...
通往来世的道路
as a pathway to the afterlife...
然而希腊人最先给它取名
but the Greeks were the first to name it.
银河来自"galacos"一词
The Milky Way comes from the word "galacos"...
是希腊语中的牛奶
which is Greek for milk.
尽管我们曾经以为我们处在宇宙的中心
And though we once believed we lived at the center of the universe...
但是 现在我们知道我们甚至都不处于
we now know that we don't even live...
我们自己星系的中心
in the center of our own galaxy.
当我们仰望夜空时
When we look up into the night sky...
我们看到这条乳白色的
and we see this milky swath of stars...
我们将其称为银河的星河
that we call the Milky Way...
我们实际上看到的是银河的旋臂
what we're actually seeing is a spiral arm of the galaxy...
它比我们更靠近银河的中心
that's closer to the center of the galaxy than we are.
我们在这里并不能真正看到银河的中心
We can't really see the center of the galaxy from here...
但是我们能够看到其中的一条旋臂
but what we can see is one of the spiral arms...
它距离中心比我们近几千光年
that's a few thousand light-years closer to the center than we are.
在我们地球这个位置注视银河
As we gaze at the Milky Way from our earthbound position...
就像看到硬币的边缘
it's like looking at the edge of a coin.
我们感觉不到银河的真实形状
We get no sense of the galaxy's real shape.
然而假如你从上端俯视星系
lf, however, you look at a galaxy from the top down...
它是个圆盘 请记住
it's a disk, remember...
就像是从上往下看一个飞碟
and it's like looking at a Frisbee from the top down.
你可以看到整个光盘
You can see its full glory.
尽管它很薄但你看不出它的厚薄
Even though it's thin, you don't see how thin it is...
但是你可以看到它整个结构
but you see its full structure.
你可以将银河比作一座城市
You can make the analogy of the Milky Way...as being very much like a city.
这是中心区
There's a central region...
有高大的建筑
there's big buildings...
中间有大量的活动
there's a lot of action in the middle...
那非常适合于我们的星系
and that's certainly true of our galaxy.
当你来到郊区
Then you move out to the suburbs...
这里的生活多了几分舒适
where life is a little bit more comfortable...
多了几分轻松
a little more relaxing.
这里是养家活口的好地方
lt's a better place to raise a family.
这里是我们安家之处
This is where we reside.
我们的太阳系位于银河系的旋臂内
Our solar system is among the Milky Way's spiral arms...
距离热闹的中心2.6万光年
26,000 light-years from the bustling center.
我们的星系非常的大
Our galaxy is so large...
地球转上一圈需要2亿多年
that it takes Earth more than 200 million years to make one lap.
太阳就位于市中心周围的普通街坊内
The Sun is located in what would be...just an average neighborhood around the city center.
然而此外如果你站在这个街坊的中间
But, again, if you stand in the middle of this neighborhood...
你根本不知道城市另一面的街坊的模样
you don't really know what the neighborhood...on the opposite side of the city looks like...
因为你无法直接看到它
because you can't see it directly.
由于我们搬出了郊区
As we move outward beyond the suburbs...
人口越发稀少
the population becomes more sparse.
对 你甚至有点偏远
And, yeah, you've even got sort of the boondocks.
在我们的星系里你看得到光环
ln our galaxy, you've got the halo...
有很年老的恒星处在星系很远的轨道上
where you have very old stars...in sort of wide orbits around the galaxy.
星系的伸展不会止步于
The galactic sprawl doesn't stop...
银河系松散不定的光环上
at the Milky Way's loose and undefined halo.
它远远超过我们的街坊
lt reaches far beyond our neighborhood...
超过了叫做本星系的星系群
and out to a group of galaxies called the Local Group.
如果你把银河系看作洛杉矶这样的城市的话
lf you think of the Milky Way galaxy...as a city like Los Angeles...
那么你可以将这些看作是加州内的所有郡县
then you can think of these as counties all within the state of California.
合在一起这个本星系就组成了整个州
And together, this Local Group makes up the entire state.
除了我们庞大的银河系
Besides our huge Milky Way...
和更大的仙女座星系外
and the even larger Andromeda galaxy...
本星系由相近的50个较小的星系组成
the Local Group consists of close to fifty smaller galaxies...
其中最近的距离约4万光年
the closest of which are roughly 40,000 light-years away.
有两个相对较近的矮星系
There are two relatively nearby dwarf galaxies...
大小麦哲伦星团
the Large and Small Clouds of Magellan...
围绕着我们的银河系
that orbit our Milky Way galaxy...
在南半球很容易观察到
and are easily seen in the southern hemisphere.
它们都是不大的小星系
They're small, little galaxies.
然而我们的本星系有几十个这样的星系
But our Local Group has several dozen such galaxies...
在里面到处游荡
sort of wandering around inside it.
大星系是少数民族
The big galaxies are the minority.
实实在在的一个优势是处于我们星系的外缘
One advantage of actually being in the outer edges of our galaxy...
我们可以更加清晰地观察到我们银河系外面的世界
we have a clearer view of outside of our Milky Way.
我们能够看到宇宙的其它部分
We're able to see the rest of the universe...
我们邻近的星系和我们本星系以外的星系群
our neighboring galaxies and galaxy clusters...beyond our own Local Group of galaxies.
银河系光环内有大量的球状星团
lnside the Milky Way's halo lie massive globular clusters.
球状星团密密麻麻挤满了恒星
Globular clusters are densely packed regions of stars...
那都是同类的东西
that are all of similar composition.
这些就像银河系里的民族聚居区
These are like the ethnic neighborhoods of the Milky Way galaxy.
事实上 这些球状星团形成时 银河系还很年强
lndeed, these globular clusters formed when the galaxy was very young.
它们是形成的第一批恒星
They are among the first stars to have formed.
有些星团年龄在120至130亿年间
Some globular clusters are twelve or thirteen billion years old.
它们包含了十亿甚至上百亿颗恒星
They contain a hundred thousand or even a million stars.
球状星团几乎和宇宙本身一样年长
Globular clusters, almost as old as the universe itself...
给了我们身处星系位置的第一个线索
gave us the first clue to our place in the galaxy.
我们看到了天上的这些球状星团
We saw these globular clusters in the sky...
但是它们的中心距离我们很远
but their centerwas somewhere far away from us.
那就是我们最先测量成果之一
And that was one of ourfirst measurements...
那应该是在星系的中间
of where the middle of the galaxy should be.
它们并不围绕着我们
They weren't orbiting around us...
而是围绕着2.7万光年以外的某个区域
but around an area somewhere about 27,000 light-years away.
我们从来没有能够足够远地从我们星系
We can never get far enough away from our own galaxy...
真正地看到它
to actually see it.
然而通过观察其他星系
But by looking at other galaxies...
比对我们对自己星系的了解
and comparing what we know about our own galaxy...
我们获得了银河系相当不错的图像
we've got a pretty good picture of the Milky Way.
在我们首次通过望远镜看到星系时
The very first time we saw galaxies through telescopes...
我们甚至都不知道它们是星系
we didn't even know they were galaxies.
我们原以为它们只是我们银河系里的星云
We thought they were just nebulae in our own galaxy...
我们只是震惊于其美丽的螺旋形状
and we were just amazed by the beautiful spiral shape.
所以自然而然 天文学家
So it was sort of natural for astronomers...
根据我们所见的它们的形态来进行分类
to classify galaxies according to their shape, what we see.
天文学家甄别出了四种基本的星系形态:
Astronomers recognize four basic galactic shapes:
椭圆状 由老龄恒星构成并不旋转
Elliptical, built of old stars and which doesn't spin...
荚状 包括了凸出部分和圆盘部分
lenticular, consisting of a bulge and a disc...
很少甚至没有新的恒星形成
and little or no new starformation...
不规则状 它完全没有实际的形状
irregular, which has no real shape at all...
比如我们本星系里的麦哲伦星云
like the Magellanic Clouds in our own Local Group...
螺旋状 包括了我们的银河系
and spiral, which includes our Milky Way.
它是个年轻和年老的恒星组成的风车
lt's a pinwheel of young and old stars...
在其中优雅地旋转
spinning gracefully through space.
很久以前人们认为有可能椭圆星系
A long time ago, people thought that maybe an elliptical galaxy
最后会塌落成螺旋星系
eventually collapses down into a spiral...
或者有可能最终所有的螺旋形系会归拢到一起
or maybe eventually spirals all come together...
形成椭圆星系
and form an elliptical.
很难弄清楚其先后次序究竟是什么
And it was sort of hard to figure out exactlywhat the sequence is.
我们清楚的一件事是椭圆星系通常是非常大的
One thing we know is that elliptical galaxies tend to be very large.
半人马座A 一个畸形椭圆星系
Centaurus A, a misshapen elliptical galaxy...
约在1300万光年以外
about thirteen million light-years away...
揭示了椭圆星系会如此之大的原因
suggests why elliptical galaxies get so big.
有许多证据证明了在那里某个地方有一个螺旋星系
There's a lot of evidence that there's a spiral galaxy in there somewhere...
被一个更大的星系所吸纳
that got absorbed by a larger galaxy.
所以此刻有可能
So, right now, it's possible...
我们所见到的这些很大的椭圆星系
that these really big elliptical galaxies we see...
是几个螺旋星系和其他类型的星系合并而成的
may be the mergers of several spirals and other types of galaxies.
我们的银河系短时期内没有被吸纳的危险
Our Milky Way isn't in danger of being absorbed any time soon.
但是 我们的螺旋星系的核心已经透露了自己的秘密
But the heart of our spiral galaxy has revealed a secret of its own.
直到最近 我们发现银河系
Only recently, we discovered that the Milky Way...
并非典型的螺旋星系 而是棒旋星系
is not a classic spiral, but a barred spiral.
有一条群星组成的棒穿过其中心
There's a bar of stars going through the center...
螺旋臂像是依附在那条棒上
and the spiral arms sort of attach offfrom that bar.
横跨2.7万光年
Spanning 27,000 light-years...
它是星系中最普通的棒
it's the most popular bar in the galaxy.
3000万颗恒星被其吸引
Thirty million stars gravitate to it.
我们星系的棒是万有引力的自然结果
The bar of our galaxy is a natural result of gravity...
每个恒星之间的相互引力作用
the mutual gravitational interactions of the individual stars...
形成了我们星系的圆盘部分和凸起部分
that form the disk of our galaxy and the bulge of our galaxy.
它有时会造成恒星挤在一起
lt causes sometimes the stars to sort of bunch up...
形成这样的棒形
into this bar configuration.
银河中心的周围是巨大的中心隆起
Surrounding the middle of the Milky Way...is a huge central bulge.
构成它的主要恒星的年岁在100至110亿年之间
lt's mostly composed of stars between ten and eleven billion years old.
凸起的大小
The size of the bulge...
关系到银河系整个最扣人心弦的特色
is linked to the Milky Way's most gripping feature of all...
一个超大质量的黑洞
a supermassive black hole.
虽然它很容易容纳进
Though it would easily fit...
地球到我们太阳之间的空间里
in the space between the Earth and our Sun...
但是它的质量是我们太阳的400万倍
it's four million times more massive than our Sun.
这听起来好像很大
Now, that sounds like a lot...
但是其它星系中心的黑洞
but other galaxies have central black holes...
其质量可以达到我们太阳的10亿倍
which extend up to a billion times the mass of our Sun.
因此 尽管我们称我们银河系中心的黑洞
So, whereas we call our black hole...
为超大质量黑洞
at the center of our Milky Way a supermassive black hole...
然而在超大质量的黑洞中它只能算是小不点
among supermassive black holes, it's kind of a runt.
黑洞无法直接观察到 因为光都无法摆脱它的魔爪
Black holes can't be seen directly because light can't escape them.
天文学家已经找到了银河的最中心点
Astronomers have located galactic ground zero...
凭借人马座里的人马座A星的射电源
through a radio source in the constellation Sagittarius...known as Sagittarius A star.
它引起了很大的骚动
lt's creating quite a stir.
我们银河系中心的黑洞在不停地旋转
The black hole in the middle of our galaxy is spinning...and it appears to be spinning...
其旋转的速度约每11分钟一圈
at a rate of about one spin per eleven minutes.
由于它的旋转 使得中心区域的恒星被其引力牢牢抓住
As it spins, central region stars caught in its gravity...
随之旋转
get swept along for the ride...
速度约300万英里/小时
orbiting it at about three million miles per hour.
黑洞影响到中心的大部分区域
The black hole affects the central region the most.
然而我们感觉不到它在拽拉地球
But we can't feel its tug on Earth...
因为我们在星系里的轨道远离中心
since we orbit the galaxy far away from the center.
银河系中心的强大力量
The colossal forces at the galaxy's heart...
被银河系不可估量的规模所抵消了
are negated by the Milky Way's unimaginable size.
对我来 银河这名字听上去就像是
To me, the name "Milky Way" sounds like something...
很舒心 很甜美糖果那样的东西
kind of comforting, sweet, you know...a candy bar, that sort of thing.
然而银河系是个怪物
But the Milky Way galaxy is a monster.
它难以想象的大
lt is incredibly huge.
所以 你想象我们的太阳系有多大时
So, when you think about howvast our solar system is...
事实上需要数年才能
the fact that it takes years...
用最快的飞船前往土星或木星
for the fastest spacecraft to get out to Saturn or Jupiter...
如果整个太阳系是CD般大小
if the entire solar system were the size of a CD...
地球是无法与银河类比的
the Earth would be comparable to the Milky Way.
它太大了
That's huge.
它绝对令人兴奋 从未停止过给我带来惊喜
That's absolutely mind-blowing, and it never ceases to amaze me.
惊喜连连不断
And the amazement goes on and on.
这个星系的喧闹和骚动
The galaxy's bustle and commotion...
可能集中在它的中心
may be concentrated in the center...
但是其壮观的螺旋臂也有自己的活动
but the spectacular spiral arms have action of their own.
在这里恒星社区正在兴建
lt's here that stellar neighborhoods are being built...
恒星不断诞生
and stars are being born.
这就是我们的星系
This is our galaxy.
好多有待进一步了解
lt's a lot to take in...
我们才开始探究其深度
and we're just beginning to probe its depths.
我们处在郊区的位置 使其很难获得全景
Our suburban location makes it difficult to get the big picture...
朦胧的宇宙尘埃云阻碍了我们的视野
and the hazy clouds of cosmic dust only block our view.
即使最强大的光学望远镜
Even the most powerful optical telescope...
也无法穿透黑暗
can't pierce the darkness.
因此 如果我们要更多地了解银河系
So, if we want to learn more about the Milky Way...
我们的观察就需要超越我们的眼睛所见的范围
we need to look beyond what our eyes can see.
虽然是广袤而虚无的空间
For all its vastness and empty space...
但是银河系异常地活跃
the Milky Way is tremendously active...
充满了惊人的现象:
and populated with some astonishing phenomena:
星团
Star clusters...
星云
nebulas...
来自其它星系的野蛮入侵者
blazing invaders from other galaxies.
科技正让我们重新审视以前的认识
Technology is making us rethink old beliefs...
正给我们显示我们以前从未考虑过的情况
and is showing us things we've never even considered before.
点火 升空
We have ignition... and lift off.
加速15秒
T-plus fifteen seconds.
我们正将新地平线飞船
We're sending the New Horizon spacecraft...
送往我们太阳系的最边缘
on its way to the very edge of our solar system.
我们生活在尘埃飞扬的宇宙间的尘埃飞扬的星系里的
We live on a dusty planet in a dusty galaxy...
尘埃飞扬的行星上
in a dusty universe.
虚无的太空并不虚无
Empty space isn't so empty.
光学望远镜只能看到最近的尘埃云
Optical telescopes can see only as far as the nearest dust cloud...
它其实并不遥远
which isn't far at all.
然而我们星系的大部分是我们看不到的
Most of our galaxy is invisible to us, however...
那是因为星系里充满了尘埃
and that's because the galaxy is full of dust...
尘埃云 可以这么说
dust clouds, if you will...
这些尘埃云遮挡了我们星系大部分恒星发出的光
and these dust clouds block the light...from most of the stars in our galaxy.
让人惊讶的是相当明亮的银河系发出的光
lt's surprising how little of the light...
这么少送到我们这里
from our rather luminous Milky Way galaxy reaches us.
其原因只是因为尘埃遮挡了它
The reason for that is simply because the dust blocks it.
然而可见光只是能谱很小的一部分
But visible light is just a small sliver of the energy spectrum...
无线电波可以抵达可见光抵达不到的地方
and radio waves rush in where visible light beams fear to tread.
在大雾天你可能无法看得很远
On a foggy day, you might not be able to see very far...
以你肉眼可见的可见光波
at visible wavelengths, which your eye can see...
但是你还是能够收听广播 观看电视
but you can still listen to your radio orwatch your TV.
无线电波穿透太空尘埃的能力
The ability of radio waves to penetrate space dust...
对研究恒星是至关重要的
is crucial to the study of the stars...
然而其使用的发现纯属偶然
but that use was discovered by accident.
1933年卡尔·扬斯基 新泽西贝尔实验室的一名工程师
ln 1933, Karl Jansky, an engineer at Bell Labs in New Jersey...
做了一个天线来捕捉跨洋电话的静电源
built an antenna to track down the source of static...on transatlantic telephone lines.
他惊讶地发现干涉
He was surprised to discover the interference...
源源不断来自我们银河系的中心
was raining down from the center of our galaxy...
人马座
the constellation Sagittarius.
用了几十年
lt took several decades...
科学家了解了扬斯基研究的东西
for scientists to realize that Jansky was on to something.
天体发出的电磁辐射
Celestial bodies emit electromagnetic radiation...
从而射电天文学诞生了
and, thus, radio astronomy was born.
但是无线电波才刚刚起步
But radio waves were just the beginning.
因为人眼无法看到所有的可用光线
Because the human eye can't see all the light that's available...
我们必须借助科技
we have to resort to technology.
观察宇宙的最佳方法之一
And one of the best ways of seeing the universe...
一个非常别样的手段就是利用红外摄像机
in a very different way is with an infrared camera.
红外摄像机只能看到热产生的波长
An infrared camera sees only the wavelengths generated by heat...
然后转换成人眼能看到的东西
then converts it to something the human eye can see.
实际上根本没有什么可见光
There actually is no visible light at all...
进入这个镜头
that passes through this lens.
这个镜头只能让热光经过
This lens only lets heat light through.
于是你就可以看到
And then you can see...
红外线里看到的所有的东西
what everything looks like in infrared light.
三 二…
Three, two...
点火…
main engine start...
2003年史匹哲太空望远镜
ln 2003, the Spitzer Space Telescope...
装备有一套红外摄像机
equipped with a battery of infrared cameras...
发射升空了
was launched into space.
探索我们宇宙的演化
...and the evolution of our universe.
其使命是探索宇宙间某些最年轻的恒星
lts mission is to explore some of the youngest stars...
和最遥远的星系
and farthest galaxies in the universe.
史匹哲装备的仪器
The instruments that Spitzer has on it...
实际上比这些摄像机强上许多倍…
are actually many times...
数百万倍
millions of times more sensitive than these cameras...
但是它们基本上是同一回事情
but they're basically the same thing.
这个机子并不是凝视天空的
This camera doesn't peer into the heavens...
但是它被消防队员用来拯救地球上的生命
but is used by firefighters to save lives right here on Earth.
摄像机可以透过烟雾弥漫的房间看到东西
The camera can see through a smoke-filled room...
读到无意识 不能动弹的受灾者的体温
to read the body heat from an unconscious or immobilized victim.
同样的技术可以让苏珊·斯托洛维
This same technology has enabled astronomer Susan Stolovy...
看到2.6万光年以外
to see 26,000 light-years away...
肉眼观察以前从未看到过的星系的中心
visualizing the center of the galaxy as never before.
这个高分辨率的拼图
This high-resolution mosaic...
是大约12000个图像拼起来的
was assembled from roughly 12,000 individual images...
来自史匹哲太空望远镜
taken from the Spitzer Space Telescope.
尽管听上去是大量的数据
Even though that sounds like a lot of data, and it is...
其实只占用了太空望远镜16个小时的时间
it only took about sixteen hours of telescope time.
星系中心这个特别的区域
This particular region of the galactic center...
跨越的空域在一个方向相当于四个满月
spans an area of the sky that's equivalent to fourfull Moons...
而另一个方向则是三个满月
in one direction and three full Moons in the other.
那相当于900光年宽 700光年高
That's the equivalent of 900 light-years across by 700 light-years high...
在户外看上去很小一部分
a small fraction of what's out there to see...
然而这成就非同小可
but a phenomenal achievement nonetheless.
就在几十年前
Just a few decades ago...
星系中心还不是研究的课题
the galactic center was not a subject of study...
因为你无法看到它
because you couldn't see it.
视觉上是看不到什么的
Visually, nothing gets through.
只有万亿分之一的光波可以穿透尘埃
Only one light wave in a trillion can penetrate the dust.
然而你进入红外线
But if you go into the infrared...
或利用射电天文学 或X射线天文学
or use radio astronomy or X-ray astronomy...
你就可以看到那里的东西
you can see what's going on there.
不同波长的电磁波谱
Different wavelengths of the electromagnetic spectrum...
可以揭示星系的方方面面
can reveal different aspects of the galaxy...
因为它们可以穿透各种天体
because they penetrate celestial objects differently.
无线电波具有最低的能量和最长的波长
Radio waves have the lowest energy or longest wavelength...
然而多数天体发射它们
but most celestial objects emit them.
接下来是红外线 可见光 紫外线
Then comes infrared, visible light, ultraviolet.
具有一个原子尺度的高能X射线
High energy X-rays with wavelengths about the size of an atom...
来自黑洞和超新星
are emitted by black holes and supernovas.
最高的能量 伽玛射线
The highest energy, gamma rays...
来自亚原子粒子的碰撞和衰变
come from the collision or decay of subatomic particles...
比如当恒星以数十亿度爆发时
like when stars explode at billions of degrees.
结合起来这些光波给了天文学家
Together, these waves give astronomers...
我们星系活动与形态更加完美的图像
a more complete picture of the activity and shape of our galaxy.
许多或许不是全部的波长
Many, if not all, of the wavelengths...
是研究宇宙所必需的
are needed to study the cosmos.
电磁波谱的不同波长
The various wavelengths of the electromagnetic spectrum...
类似于小提琴的琴弦
are similar to the strings on a violin.
乐曲中 声音的各种波长
ln music, many wavelengths of sound...
被用来表达音乐思想
are used to communicate a musical idea.
这一段从低到高变化很大
This piece has a very large range...from a low note to a high note.
如果我们把自己限制在可见光的范围内
lfwe were to restrict ourselves to the visible light spectrum...
那几乎就像我们只能听到那段当中的两个音符
it's almost as if we were only to hear two notes...in the middle of that piece.
交替使用各种波长
Using alternate wavelengths...
我们观察的越多 发现也就越多
the more we look, the more we're discovering.
就在最近我们发现有两个小星系
Just recently, we've discovered that there are two small galaxies...
正在与银河系碰撞
colliding with the Milky Way right now...
我们不知道它们在哪里的唯一的原因
and the only reason we didn't know they were there...
就是因为有太多的尘埃
is because there was so much dust...
存在于我们的影戏圆盘中但我们无法看到它们
in the disk of our galaxy, we couldn't see them.
我们生活在云里雾里
We're living inside this cloud...
有些情况我们一点都不知道
and it's something we're not aware of.
然而用上了红外线你就可以穿透那尘埃了
But with infrared light, you can cut through that dust.
在我们将红外望远镜转向天空的那一刻
And the minute we turned infrared telescopes to the sky...
我们看到这些小星系就在上方 冲着我们过来
we saw these little galaxies up there, coming right at us.
从我们在银河系的斜视位置看去
From our cockeyed position in the Milky Way...
很难判断出我们星系的真是模样
it's difficult to gauge what our galaxy really looks like.
射电和光学天文学让我们能一瞥其模样
Radio and optical astronomy give us a glimpse of its features...
然而要获得其全貌 我们就必须到外面去看了
but to get the big picture, we need to look outward.
所以我们增强对我们自己的星系的认识的途径
So the waywe gain some understanding of our own galaxy...
就是首先通过观察其它星系
is, first of all, by looking at other galaxies...
观察它们的模样 观察其它星系中的情况
and seeing what they look like and seeing things in other galaxies...
那相当于我们观察自己星系的情况
that correspond to things that we see in our own galaxy...
像气体云沿着像是旋臂排列的样子
like clouds of gas that are kind of lined up...along what looks like a spiral arm.
知道吗 我们可以看到我们自己星系的部分旋臂
You know, we can see parts of spiral arms in our own galaxy...
我们估摸它们整个联系在一起
and we figure that they're all connected...
有点像我们可以从外面看到的其它星系的旋臂
kind of like the spiral arms of other galaxies...that we can see from the outside.
我们知道银河系的四条主要的旋臂
We know that the Milky Way's four main spiral arms...
从闹市区像大街那样展开
swing out from the downtown center like wide streets.
从里到外给它们分别取名:矩尺座旋臂
From the inside out, they're named Norma...
南十字座旋臂
Scutum-Crux...
人马座旋臂
Sagittarius...
英仙座旋臂
and Perseus.
假如旋臂是星系的郊区的话
lfthe arms are the galaxy's suburbs...
那么我们的太阳系就居住在安静的大街尽头
then our solar system lives on a quiet, dead-end street...
在人马座旋臂和英仙座旋臂之间的所谓猎户座支臂上
between Sagittarius and Perseus on what's called the Orion Spur.
银河系里所有的恒星
All the stars in the Milky Way...
组成了一个约2000到4000亿的社会
add up to a community of about 200 to 400 billion...
它们都在移动之中
and they're on the move.
我们围绕着星系运转
We are orbiting around the galaxy.
我们改变了我们的位置
We change our position.
迄今为止 我们认为太阳总是
So far, we think the Sun has always been...
与中心保持着同样的距离
about the same distance away from the center...
但是我们已经进出了
but we've been in and out...
那里几乎所有的旋臂
of pretty much every spiral arm that there is.
螺旋形被称为密度波
The spirals are called density waves...
那里的恒星和气体被推挤在一起
areas where the stars and gas get pushed together.
由于密度波的盘旋
As the density waves spiral around...
数十亿颗恒星穿行其中
the billions of stars ride over and through them.
一旦你想起环法自行车赛
When you think about watching the Tour de France...
你就可以看到所有的那些自行车
and you see all of these bicycles.
他们都在向前行进
They're all moving forward.
有时他们会簇拥在一条车道上
Sometimes they kind of clump up around one bicyclist.
有时他们会绵延而行
And sometimes they're stretched out.
那有点像旋臂的模样
That's sort of what the spiral arms are like...
恒星就像赛车那样转动
that the stars are going around like the bicyclists...
有时在成堆簇拥的地区
sometimes in clumpy areas...
有时在绵延伸展的区域
and sometimes in more spread-out areas...
但是它们都围绕着中心运转
but they keep going around the center.
恒星通常不单独行动
Stars don't usually travel alone.
与此同时 球状星团居住在星系的光环里
While giant globular clusters populate the galaxy's halo...
银河盘已经散开 即银河星团
the galactic disk has open or galactic clusters.
这些成堆的年轻恒星
These bundles of young stars...
就靠它们之间的引力结合在一起
are barely held together by their mutual gravity.
现在 "疏散星团"意味着恒星实际上可以自由来去
Now, "open cluster" implies that the stars are actually free to go.
它是开放的
lt is open.
因此通常这个星团
So this is a cluster, usually...
是由许多恒星结合在一起形成的
of many stars that have formed together...
都是来自这些巨大的尘埃和气体云其中的一个
all from one of these giant clouds of dust and gas.
随着时间的推移它们将相互远离
Over time, they're going to move away from each other...
分别散布在星系四处
distribute themselves around the galaxy.
天文学家已经计算出了银河系里约有两万个疏散星团
Astronomers have counted about 20,000 open clusters in the galaxy.
昴宿星团是已知最接近地球的一个
The Pleiades is the one found nearest to the Earth.
它形成于1亿年前
lt formed a hundred million years ago...
它至少还有两倍的时间
and will be around at least twice that long...
才会被银河系的旋臂撕碎
before the galaxy's spiral arms tear it apart.
话说回来我们的太阳在孤独地运转
Closer to home, our own Sun, orbiting in solitude...
或许曾经就是疏散星团里恒星的一部分
may have once been part of an open-cluster star...
独自闯荡出来的
that struck out on its own.
太阳 星团 我们自己的地球
The Sun, the star clusters, our own planet...
事实上整个星系以至于宇宙
in fact, the entire galaxy and the universe beyond...
都是尘埃和气体构成的
are built of dust and gases.
现在阻碍我们视线的这些粒子
These particles that now block ourview...
一开始就让我们来到了这里
are what got us here in the first place...
恒星制造机器依然在不停地捣鼓
and the star-making machinery is still cranking.
没有什么比得上辉煌的日落景观
Nothing beats the spectacle of a glorious sunset...
然而我们应将它归功于尘埃和气体
but we owe it all to dust and gas.
夕阳表现出黄 橙甚至红色有两个原因
The setting Sun appears yellow, orange, or even red for two reasons.
首先大气层里的大气分子
First of all, the molecules of air in the atmosphere...
将紫 蓝 绿光驱赶出了我们的视线
are scattering the violet, blue, and green light...out of our line of sight...
留下黄 橙 红色进入我们眼帘
leaving the yellows, oranges, and reds to reach our eyes.
第二 大气层中尘埃或烟雾这样的微粒吸收蓝光
And second of all, particles like dust or smoke...or smog in the atmosphere absorb blue light...
要多于它们吸收红光
more than they do red light.
甚至宏伟的蓝天其实是一种错觉
Even the grandeur of a blue sky is really an optical illusion.
天空为什么是蓝的呢？
Why is the sky blue?
我们的大气层中根本没有什么蓝色的气体
There's nothing blue about the gases of our atmosphere...
但是由于阳光透过我们的大气层
but as sunlight comes through our atmosphere...
较短波长的蓝光
the shorterwavelengths, the blue light...
其散射要甚于较长的波长
get scattered more than the longerwavelengths do.
所以你注视天空任何特定的部分
So if you look at any particular part of the sky...
你极有可能看到蓝光
you're more likely to see blue light...
被散射到你的眼中
being scattered towards your eye.
太空一团漆黑是因为没有足够的气体或尘埃微粒
Space is dark because there aren't enough gas or dust particles...
来反射数十亿颗星光
to reflect the light of a billion stars.
虽然太空可能是空无一物 但是并不完美
And though space may be a vacuum, it's not perfect.
银河盘 银河系最大的部分
The galactic disk, the largest portion of the Milky Way...
其质量的15%左右是尘埃和气体
owes about fifteen percent of its mass to dust and gas.
气体云可以跨越数百甚至数千光年
Gas clouds can span hundreds or even thousands of light-years...
为星系栩栩发光提供了原料
providing the raw material that fires the galaxy.
宇宙尘埃和气体的区域称为星云
These regions of cosmic dust and gas are called nebulae...
它们产生的效果可以和地球上所见到的一切相媲美
and they produce effects rivaling anything seen on Earth.
一个很好的例子就是猎户座星云
A good example is the Orion Nebula...
在猎户座里
in the constellation Orion.
这个区域活跃着恒星的形成
This region is active with stellarformation...
使得恒星周围的气体光芒四射
which makes the gas around the stars glow.
它在星云旁的巨星发出的光线照射下荧光烁烁
lt's literally fluorescing in response to the light...coming out of the massive stars that are near the nebula...
这个星云通体被照亮 清晰可见
and this nebula literally glows and can be seen.
你用肉眼就能看到它
You can see it with your naked eye.
你看到猎户座星云时
When you see the Orion Nebula...
一定程度上 这些对我们来说是早期的图像
in a real way, those are baby pictures for us.
50亿年前 我们就是在一个发光的热星云里
Five billion years ago, we were in a glowing hot nebula...
太阳和行星一道形成
and the Sun and the planets were forming together...
受到引力的影响
under the influence of gravity.
猎户座 里面包含了高温星体
Orion, which contains hot stars...
紫外线电离它的气体
ionizing its gases with ultraviolet light...
被称为弥散或发射星云
is called a diffuse or emission nebula.
天文学家分类了其他两类星云
Astronomers classify two other categories of nebulae.
有些星云就是被称为发射星云的那一类
Some nebulae are what are called reflection nebulae.
它们很简单 这些星云里的尘埃
They're simply... the dust in these nebulae...
只是反射附近的亮星的星光
is simply reflecting the starlight from the bright star nearby.
女巫头星云是反射星云的一个例子
The Witch Head Nebula is an example of a reflection nebula...
借助于参宿七的星光
borrowing light from the star Rigel.
反射星云表现出蓝光的原因一如我们的天空
Reflection nebulae appear blue for the same reason our sky does.
蓝光的反射比红光更加容易
Blue light is more easily reflected than red.
最后是马头星云这样的暗星云
And last there are dark nebulae like the Horsehead.
一旦像我们太阳这样的低质量的恒星死亡后
When low-mass stars like our Sun die...
它们就会形成另一类星云叫做行星状星云
they form another kind of nebula called a planetary nebula.
这些昏暗的寿命短暂的星云像猫眼星云
These dim, short-lived nebulae, like the Cat's Eye Nebula...
会将元素喷射回星系
spew elements back into the galaxy.
这些会成为新太阳和新行星的原料
These may become raw materials for new suns and new planets.
就像垂死的恒星喷出尘埃和气体云
Just as dying stars spew out clouds of dust and gas...
尘埃和气体会结合在一起形成恒星一样
dust and gas can come together to form stars.
在建筑工地上你看到旧建筑被推倒
At a construction site, you have old buildings being torn down...
新建筑在建起
and new buildings going up.
这几乎和银河系一模一样
And it's very much the same in the Milky Way galaxy.
你看到老恒星爆发
You have old stars explode...
它们抛出新材料 原材料
and they cast out new material, raw material...
气体和尘埃可以用来形成新的恒星
gas and dust that can be used to form new stars.
星云是星系的回收中心
Nebulae are the galaxy's recycling centers...
在这里变废为宝
where old becomes new again.
回收利用不只是地球上的好主意
Recycling is not just a good idea here on Earth.
它是宇宙的自然法则
lt's a natural cosmic law.
事实上 我们的人体都是用回收的材料造就的
ln fact, our own bodies are made out of recycled material...
来自早几代的恒星
from earlier generations of stars...
材料被分解成为星际介质
that had dispersed material into the interstellar medium...
那是我们太阳系形成之前的事
before our own solar system formed.
各代恒星都创造出了重元素
Each generation of stars creates heavier elements...
成为宇宙万物的组成部分
which become the ingredients for everything in the universe.
星系大部分高温 年轻的恒星
Most of the galaxy's hot, young stars...
是在银河系的旋臂里形成的
get built in the Milky Way's spiral arms.
由于气体云如恒星那样围绕着星系中心运转
As gas clouds orbit the center of the galaxy like the stars do...
在穿越旋臂时遭到了挤压
they get squeezed as they go through a spiral arm.
请记住旋臂仅仅是群星表现出的波
Remember, a spiral arm is simply a wave in the pattern of stars.
因为群星积聚在那里
And because stars are denser there...
经过其中的气体云往往会被挤压
the gas clouds that orbit through it tend to get compressed.
那种挤压产生引力让气体抱团
That compression allows gravity to get a hold of that gas...
导致它坍缩形成恒星
and cause it to collapse to form stars...
要比其他地方更加容易
more readily there than anywhere else.
恒星通常消亡在旋臂里
Stars often die in the spiral arms...
因为它们在这里形成更加频繁
because they are formed here more frequently...
它们中的牺牲者拥有巨大的质量
victims of their own enormous mass.
较大质量的恒星非常强大
The more massive stars are extremely powerful...
非常明亮
extremely luminous.
为了达到那样的亮度
And to be that luminous...
它们不得不很快地消耗自己的能源
they have to use up their energy source very quickly.
因此大质量恒星的寿命很短
So massive stars live only short lives...
它们于是就定居或靠近自己的出生地 旋臂里
and they are thus found in or near their birthplaces, the spiral arms...
因为它们根本没有足够的时间
because they simply don't have enough time...
离开自己出生的地方
to wander away from the places where they were born.
尽管我们可以预期一些恒星的未来
Although we can anticipate the future of some stars...
但是往往很难了解它们的历史
it's often difficult to learn their history.
然而新科技正在揭示已经充分研究的
But new techniques are revealing new secrets...
银河系里一颗叫做Mira A的恒星的秘密
about a well-studied star in the Milky Way called Mira A.
Mira 实际上是天文学家400年来一直很感兴趣的恒星
Mira has actually been a favorite star of astronomers for 400 years.
它是夜空中很容易看到的恒星
lt's a very easily visible star in the night sky.
最近星系演化探测器(GALEX)
Recently, the GALEX spacecraft, the Galaxy Evolution Explorer...
以看不见的紫外线拍摄了Mira
photographed Mira in invisible ultraviolet light...
揭示出它在背后留下了13光年的足迹
and revealed that it's leaving a trail thirteen light-years long behind it.
我们认为那实际上的原因是基于
We think that's actually caused by the fact...
由于它穿过气体
that as the star plows through the gas...
气体随之加热激起震荡
the gas heats up in a bow shock...
非常像船只激起波澜
very much like waves breaking up against a boat.
于是那气流随着热物质流出
And then that streams out into a wake of hot material.
你其实看到了Mira的活动 很大程度像条船
You're actually looking at Mira acting very much like a boat...
劈波斩浪
plowing through the water.
一旦你看到Mira现在有多快
When you look at howfast Mira's going right now...
大约29.1万英里/小时
about 291,000 miles an hour...
你就可以计算出
and you do the calculations...
它那长长的尾巴是它最后的3万年
that long tail is its path the last 30,000 years.
我们无法准确预测太阳在其围绕着银河
We can't predict exactly where the Sun will go...
运行的轨道上的具体位置
in its orbit around the Milky Way.
有各种因素会对其产生影响
There's all kinds of things it could interact with.
但是我们掌握了我们太阳的历史
But here we have the history of one star.
我们知道这是它走的路
We know this is the path it took.
那将帮助我们模拟星系运作的情况
And that'll help us model how the galaxyworks...
以及所有的恒星是如何围绕着星系中心运行的
and how all the stars move around the middle of the galaxy.
在银河的郊区旋臂里
Within the Milky Way's suburban spiral arms...
年轻的恒星拥有足够的活动空间
young stars enjoy plenty of space to move around.
一旦我们来到星系的凸出部分
As we move into the galactic bulge...
状况就变得拥挤不堪
conditions get much more crowded and urban.
最靠近太阳的恒星
The closest star to the Sun...
位于四光年多的地方
is a little more than four light-years away.
当我们注视夜空时
And when we look up into the night sky...
即使是在周围没有亮光的十分晴朗的夜晚
even on a perfectly clear night with no lights around...
你所看到的星星不可能超过2000或者3000颗
you can't see more than about 2,000 or 3,000 stars.
然而 一旦我们的地球身处银河中心
But if our planet was down in the middle of the galaxy...
那么夜空中就会有百万颗星星
there would be a million stars in the night sky...
最亮的恒星的亮度是我们在空中从未见过的
as bright as the brightest star that we've ever seen in our sky.
它将非常的亮 事实上没有夜晚
And it would be so bright that, in fact, it wouldn't be nighttime.
将始终是白昼
lt would be daytime all the time.
不用多说 生活将完全不同
Life, as we know it, would be completely different.
那么我们要把我们的位置放在什么地方呢？
So what do we owe our position to?
科学家认为引力做了大量的工作
Scientists believe that gravity has a lot to do with it.
引力是驱动星系的动力
Gravity is the power that drives the galaxy...
在星系的中心 搅动着它提供动力的引擎
and at the galaxy's center, churns the engine it feeds.
星系就像座城市 里面始终在不断变化
Galaxies are like a city in that they are ever-changing...
不断地重建和复兴
and you're constantly being rebuilt and reinvigorated.
毫无疑问银河系
There's no question that the Milky Way...
几十亿年前
a few billion years ago...
其模样与今天的模样有很大的不同
looked a lot different than it does today.
它可能更小些
lt probably was smaller.
可能不具备我们今天所见的美丽的螺旋状
lt probably didn't have the beautiful spiral shape...that we see today.
随着物体在引力作用下塌落 自然而然就形成了圆盘
As things collapse under gravity, you tend to naturally form a disk.
你会注意到圆盘无处不在
You'll notice there are disks everywhere.
我们的太阳系是圆盘 我们的星系是圆盘
Our solar system is a disk, our galaxy is a disk.
所以 所有的恒星都向同一个方向运转
So the stars all start rotating in the same direction.
就像一座城市星系里并非所有的恒星都是本地人
Just as in a city, not all of the stars in the galaxy are natives.
有些恒星出生在银河系之外
Some stars, born beyond the Milky Way...
落户在这 并且开始暂露头角
settle here and begin to make their mark.
然而另一方面 如果有另一个星系经过
But then, if another galaxy comes by...
引力会影响到恒星移动的路径
the gravity affects the way the stars move...
它就可能加入到旋臂里
and this may initiate the spiral arms.
因此 事实上我们的螺旋状可能就是某种证据
So, in fact, our spiral shape may be some evidence...
说明银河系是由多个小星系
that the Milky Way is composed of more than one small galaxy...
在很久以前走在一起构成的
that came together a long time ago.
在历史上星系的中心
Historically, the center of the galaxy...
一直存在着一个难以看透的秘密
has been an impenetrable mystery...
直到我们开发出X射线观察
until we developed X-ray vision.
我们真正识别出银河系中心的准确位置
One of the first ways we really identified...
的一个最早的手段
where the exact center of the galaxywas...
就是利用X射线望远镜
was with an X-ray telescope.
X射线能够穿透
Well, the X-rays were able to pass through...
我们星系盘里所有的尘埃和气体
all of the dust and gas in the disk of our galaxy.
因此 尽管我们无法真正看到星系明亮的中心
And so, even though we can't really see this bright center to the galaxy...
但是在X射线里 这个巨大的 熊熊燃烧的热源
in X-rays, there's this giant, glowing hot source...
就在中央
right in the middle.
X射线发射体 人马座A星
The X-ray emitter, Sagittarius A star...
联系着银河系中心的超大质量的黑洞
is associated with the supermassive black hole...in the Milky Way's center.
按照定义黑洞不允许光甚至X射线逃逸
By definition, a black hole doesn't allow light...or even X-rays to escape.
气体的辐射射物被黑洞引力困住
The radiation comes from gas caught in its gravity...
旋转并加热到数百万度
spun and heated to millions of degrees.
它们的移动速度极高
They're moving at extremely high velocities.
比如我们已经能够观察到的更为极端的案例
For example, the more extreme cases that we've been able to observe...
恒星在经过黑洞时
the stars are moving as they pass by the black hole...
其速度达到了一万公里/秒
at a speed of10,000 kilometers per second.
那就像在四秒钟里绕地球一圈
That's like going around the world in four seconds.
我们谈到了整个恒星以那样的速度移动
And we're talking about a whole star moving at that speed.
我们看到了恒星围绕着我们银河系的最中心运转
When we watch stars orbiting the very center of our galaxy...
显然那里有某种看不见的怪物
it's obvious that there's some sort of invisible monster there.
它们都围绕着一个巨大的质量运转
They're orbiting around a giant mass.
恒星的运转暗示着
And the orbits of the stars imply that there's about...
大约是太阳3到4百万倍的质量
three to four million times the mass of the Sun...
存在于我们星系的最中心
in the very center of our galaxy.
我们不清楚谁先出现 是星系呢 还是黑洞
We're not sure which came first, the galaxy or the black hole...
但是我们知道它是存在的 是个庞然大物
but we know that it's there, and it's tremendous.
虽然它强大又怪异 但这个超大质量黑洞
For all its power and weirdness, the supermassive black hole...
对银河系这样大小的星系是相当典型的
is pretty typical for a galaxy the size of the Milky Way.
其它螺旋形系和大椭圆星系
Other spiral galaxies and big elliptical galaxies...
它们的中心似乎也有超大质量黑洞
also seem to have supermassive black holes in their middle...
范围从我们太阳质量的100万倍
ranging from a million times the mass of our Sun...
一直到我们太阳质量的几十亿倍
up to several billion times the mass of our Sun.
围绕黑洞的恒星都上年岁了
The stars surrounding the black hole are ancient.
许多是比我们太阳大数百倍的红巨星
Many are red giants, hundreds oftimes bigger than our Sun.
银河的中心挤满了它们
The galactic center is crowded with them...
就像市中心里人满为患
like an urban downtown crowded with people.
恒星和人一样爱出风头
And stars, like people, can be pushy.
银河系中心的多数恒星
Most stars in the galactic center...
只是围绕着中心黑洞不停地运转
simplyjust keep orbiting the central black hole.
然而在银河中心
But in the galactic center...
有太多的恒星相互挤得很近
there are so many stars packed so close together...
以至于恒星始终在相互推搡
that stars are constantly nudging each other...
一点点引力
a little bit gravitationally.
它们的轨道一直遭到干扰
And their orbits are being perturbed...
少许遭到改变
changed a little bit.
遭受碰撞的恒星会被剥夺走大气层
A bumped star can get stripped of its atmosphere...
只留下其运转的核心部分
leaving just its orbiting core.
或者难得会滚进黑洞然后消失得无影无踪
Or, rarely, it can tumble into the black hole and vanish.
然而还有事情正发生在黑洞的周围
But something else is happening around the black hole.
这个动荡不安的地区
This turbulent, dangerous neighborhood...
也是个恒星育婴所
is also a stellar nursery.
我们观察到的正飞快地围绕着黑洞运转的恒星
The stars that we're observing...moving fastest around the black hole...
都是最近才形成的年轻恒星
are the young stars that have very recently formed.
那个情况被我们称之为青春悖论
And it's something we call the paradox of youth...
因为很难想象是如何在黑洞面前
because it's hard to imagine how to form...
形成这些大量的年轻恒星的
these massive young stars in the presence of a black hole...
可是它们就在那里
and yet there they are.
近来科学家发现了
Recently, astronomers discovered...
并非所有的恒星都受黑洞的掌控
that not all stars caught in the black hole's grip...
注定要呆在那里的
are doomed to stay there.
有些会设法逃脱去拜访宇宙
A few manage to break away and see the universe.
高速行走在宇宙间
Barreling through the universe...
时速达150万英里
at one and a half million miles per hour...
超高速恒星是星系的逃亡者
hyper-velocity stars are the escapees of the galaxy.
高速恒星的有趣之处在于
And what's interesting about high-velocity stars...
解释它们极端的速度的唯一方法
is the only way to explain their extreme velocities...
就是它们是被超大质量的黑洞弹射出来
is that they were ejected by a supermassive black hole.
恒星要被弹射
For a star to go ballistic...
要采取一套非常特殊的环境
takes a very specific set of circumstances...
事实上它需要两个恒星
and, in fact, it requires two stars.
你抬头看到的大多数恒星
Most of the stars you see in the sky...
并不是单个的恒星 而是成双成对的恒星
are not single stars, but pairs or binary stars.
它们相互围绕运转 依靠引力联系在一起
They orbit around each other, linked by gravity's embrace.
然而银河中心的恒星对子
But a star pair in the galactic center...
可能会遭到周围恒星的推挤
might getjostled by surrounding stars...
在黑洞很近的地方游荡
and stray too close to the black hole.
一旦发生这种情况
When that happens...
此刻黑洞的引力
the moment that the gravitational pull of the black hole...
就会超过把两颗恒星约束在一起的引力
exceeds the gravity that's binding the two stars together...
这对恒星就会被扯开
the pair of stars is broken apart.
其中的一颗恒星就会被黑洞抓住
One of the stars will be captured by the black hole...
通常会进入围绕黑洞的非常贴近的轨道
usually into a very tight orbit around the black hole...
而另一颗恒星则会获得
and the other star will then gain...
其系统的全部能量 会以难以置信的速度弹出
all the energy of that system and it'll be ejected...with this incredible velocity.
如果星系是个城市的话
lf the galaxy were a city...
那么大多数的恒星就是汽车或行人
where most of the stars would be cars or pedestrians...
高速恒星就更像是冲出城市的飞机或高速列车
a high-velocity star would be more like an airplane...or a high-speed train rushing out of the country.
如果你呆在一个高速恒星上驾乘是相当惊人的
lf you were on a high-velocity star, the ride would be quite amazing.
天上布满了恒星
The sky would be covered with stars...
四面八方如满月般的亮星
as bright as the full Moon in every direction.
但是那种景观很快就会改变
But that view would quickly change...
因为高速恒星很快就飞出了星系
'cause the high-velocity star moves so quickly out of the galaxy...
星星在夜空中会越来越稀少
the stars would appear fewer and fewer in the night sky.
银河系在不断地运动
The galaxy is constantly in motion...
就像是一个巨大的轮子或不断延伸的大都会
like a giant wheel or a sprawling metropolis.
在城市的中心
ln the heart of town...
超大质量黑洞的引力搅动着周围的恒星
the supermassive black hole's gravity whips stars around...
约11分钟转动一圈
in an orbit of around eleven minutes.
地球坐落的位置 是在一条旋臂三分之二的地方
Where the Earth sits, two-thirds of the way out on a spiral arm...
我们穿越银河系 每次需要2.5亿年
we traverse the Milky Way once every 250 million years.
我们的太阳系走完街区
Our solar system has been around the block...
自形成以来只有18次
only eighteen times since it formed.
银河系难以估摸的尺度
The Milky Way's incomprehensible size...
使它很容易忘记自己只是
makes it easy to forget it's just one small part...
不断膨胀的宇宙的很小一部分
of an expanding universe.
人们听说膨胀的宇宙时
When people hear about the expanding universe...
普遍的误解就是一切都在膨胀之中
a common misconception is that everything is expanding.
事实上我现在就没有膨胀
And in fact, l'm not expanding right now.
我的原子大小没变
My atoms are the same size.
我的细胞大小没变
My cells are the same size.
地球也没有渐渐远离太阳
The Earth is not getting farther away from the Sun.
宇宙的膨胀只适用于天体
The expansion of the universe only applies to celestial objects...
并未因为引力而结合在一起
that aren't bound together by gravity.
因为银河系里的行星
Since the planets within the Milky Way...
受到的引力拉扯要强于
have stronger gravitational pulls...
我们外部星系的张力
than the expanding forces outside our galaxy...
所以宇宙的膨胀并未影响到我们太阳系
the expansion of the universe doesn't affect our solar system.
我们自己的银河系 一个螺旋形系
Our own Milky Way, a spiral galaxy...
已经遭到了另一个螺旋形系的碰撞
is on a collision course with another spiral galaxy...
我们附近最大的螺旋星系
the largest spiral near us...
它就是仙女座星系
and that is the Andromeda galaxy.
我们认为或许在3 40亿年间
We think that in maybe three orfour billion years...
我们两个星系会结合在一起
our two galaxies may merge together.
看到那样的情景是非常有趣的事
lt will be very interesting to see what happens.
或许不会发生恒星的碰撞
What probably won't happen is a collision of stars.
尽管两个星系包含了数十亿颗恒星
Even though both galaxies contain billions of stars...
但是它们之间的距离是非常大的
the space between them is enormous.
它们会有引力的相互作用
They will gravitationally interact...
改变它们的方向和运动
changing their direction and motion.
最终 联姻的螺旋星系将尘埃落定
Eventually, the merged spirals will settle down...
成为一个椭圆星系
to become an elliptical galaxy.
从本质上讲 我们本星系里所有几十个星系
Essentially, all of the several dozen galaxies in our local group...
都会成为一个超星系的一部分
will be part of one supergalaxy.
于是慢慢地超星系会开始丧失恒星
And then, gradually, that supergalaxy will start losing stars...
原因就在于那个星系里的恒星之间的引力作用
because of gravitational interactions among the stars within that galaxy.
有些会飞进星系之间的太空
Some will get flung away into intergalactic space.
在它最初形成时银河系快速形成群星
When it first formed, the Milky Way built stars at a rapid pace...
利用大爆炸喷射进太空里的原材料
using raw materials that were ejected in space from the Big Bang.
随着星系年龄的增大
As the galaxy aged...
恒星的生产从每年几百个慢慢降到
the star production slowed down from a few hundred a year...
如今每年4到6个新恒星
to about four to six new stars each year today.
随着时间的推移银河系变化天翻地覆
Over time, the Milky Way galaxy has changed dramatically...
我们不能确切地知道它很久以前的样子
and we don't know exactly what it looked like long ago.
然而有可能在早期有过大量的气体和尘埃
But probably early on, there was a lot more gas and dust...
或许还有少量的恒星
and probably fewer stars.
你看到很多质量很大的恒星
And you had a lot ofvery large, very massive stars...
它们不是早期形成的
that would've formed early on.
这些早期的恒星很快就爆发了
And these early stars exploded fantastically...
吐出了新材料 重金属
and spat out new material, heavier metals...
可以用来形成年幼的第二代
that could be used to form smaller second-generation...
然后是第三代恒星
and then third-generation stars.
有些年轻的星系仍然陶醉于此类建筑潮
Some younger galaxies are still enjoying that kind of building boom.
我们可以看到有些星系
We can see some galaxies...
那里的恒星形成的速度相对我们星系是相当地快
where the rate of star formation is very high...compared to our galaxy.
它们被称为星暴星系
Those are called starburst galaxies.
恒星形成的速度都可以是
The rate of starformation there can be anywhere...
我们现在星系的10到100倍
from ten to a hundred times what it is now in our galaxy.
伴随着一代又一代 恒星的生产慢慢减缓
With every generation, star production slows down...
银河系的这个业务已经开展了130亿年了
and the Milky Way has been in business for thirteen billion years.
我们星系恒星形成的速度
One of the reasons that the rate of star formation in our galaxy...
随着时间改变 从很快的速度
has changed over time, going from a very high rate...
变为现在适度的恒星形成速度的原因之一
to the current modest rate of star formation...
就是因为气体正在枯竭
is because the gas is being used up.
气体的消耗是为了形成恒星
Gas is used up to form stars.
我们正在耗尽气体 一点没错
And we're running out of gas, literally.
最终数万亿年后恒星的形成终将完全停止
Eventually, over trillions of years, starformation will stop completely.
伟大的星系建设项目将终结
The great galactic construction project will shut down...
闪烁的恒星一个接着一个将逐渐消亡
and one by one, the twinkling stars will fade away.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing